[music]
>> Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition 2026 release wave one.
My name is Aleksandar Totovic, I'm a
product manager, and I will show what's
new in excise taxes or excise duties.
So,
let's first look in a Business Central.
Even we started with this functionality
already in previous wave, I still want
to emphasize that this is really
important because excise tax calculation
regulatory is extremely important for
all users, all customers who are
handling with
excise taxes or duties in their regular
work. If you definitely minimize risk of
penalties because now they are on
control and they can calculate all of
them automatically in a Business
Central. And of course, operational
efficiency because they do not need to
repeat and manually to calculate all
these taxes or duties all the time.
So,
as I mentioned, this is something what
we continue from previous wave. So,
excise taxes framework officially has
been delivered in 2025 wave release wave
two.
But in this moment, we had only
framework and two options for
calculation, CBAM and EPR.
>> [snorts]
>> Both of them, carbon border adjustment
mechanism and
environmental all these environmental
and sustainability calculations. So,
both of them were really important to be
on a time. So, when we started to work
about them, we
saw that this is almost the same model
as all other excise types. So, we said,
"Okay, let's build excise journal
and we will use excise journal for both
of these CBAM and EPR calculations. So,
now we already have them inside from
previous wave, but in this wave, we
extended it to much more options. So,
what does it mean? We support other
excise types.
And
when I say other excise types, I do not
want to count them because this is
configurable. You can use for many, many
different excise types. We have some
ideas, we have some different tax bases,
so you you're limited with tax
calculation models, but
behind all these calculation models, if
you want to use them, if all of them are
good for you, they are configurable and
you can use different tax calculations.
So, excise journal,
this is something what we already had
earlier. So, you could choose CBAM, EPR,
or excise taxes models. But if you
choose excise tax model, you need to
choose exactly which
excise type you want to use. This is
what I said. CBAM, EPR, they are
independent calculation, but for all our
other excise taxes, this is excise type
and you need to choose which one you
want to use. What do we have in a
excise journal? We have excise journal
template batch, just standard journal,
as you already have it all other
journals in a Business Central. And once
when you post or not post actually, but
registering, you will get excise taxes
at transaction logs.
So,
how you will start with
specifying different excise taxes behind
CBAM and EPR?
You will find excise tax types. So, this
is not so complicated for setting up.
You have code, description, and then
what is important, you have tax bases.
Tax bases actually heart of this system.
You need to choose how you will collect
information about excise taxes.
Are they based on weight
or volume, quantity, sugar content, pure
alcohol content, active content? So, you
have different models, six different
models, how you will calculate and what
what will be used as a calculation for
this excise taxes.
Okay, you have one field where you can
enable disable this calculation in one
moment. And the last one, reporting is
how you will expose these fields on your
journal. We just wanted to avoid
misunderstanding if you have the if you
are working with different excise taxes
to have only excise tax field. So, you
will get in a bracket exactly name you
have here in a reporting caption. So,
this is plastic tax or sugar tax, it
will be easier to see when you open
journal.
So, for all of these excise tax types,
you need to
add
um
how from where you want to collect this
information. So, now we know how we want
because quantity, volume, or some other
options, but now from where to collect.
We will collect this information using
these connected field table entry
permissions. And from there, you can
choose different entry types.
So, what does it mean? Some excise taxes
are based on a purchase, some excise
taxes are based on a sales. So, you can
configure what you want to use.
So, you have all these six options.
Purchase.
And if this is incoming, positive
adjustment, output, or assembly output,
if this is about production, or if this
is from um
uh sales process, you can use sales or
eventually negative adjustment. So, you
can configure what you want to use and
what you have. So, for example, if you
have production, you can use output. If
you do not have production, you don't
need to have this configured.
And the last one is you need to
configure excise duty rates.
Um in probably more than 95% probably
almost all
all possible cases, you will use excise
duties on items. But still, in some rare
situations, it can happen that you need
to calculate based on fixed assets. So,
you can use for both of them, item and
fixed assets. And you need to go to
excise duty rates. And if you have fixed
asset, you will just add one new line
that you will use for fixed assets. And
you need to configure what will be
excise duty rate.
This is not percent because they are not
we do not use as a percentage on some
specific value.
This is let's say limitation.
We do not use as well our model. Only
model is configured that you will use
fixed fast
excise duty rate based on some specific
model of calculation.
So,
how does it work? Now you have full
workflow for excise journal calculation.
When you run calculation, first system
will look to identify all excise types
you have there. And based on these
excise types, system will search through
entries to find appropriate entries.
What does it mean? It means if you
configure purchase, sales, output,
whatever you configure there, system
will try to locate all these entries
with
specific types. Then based on that,
system will use dedicated tax bases you
have configured on your excise tax types
and calculate excise duty rate. How it
works in general, system will take
quantity from
item journal from item ledger entry,
multiply with a quantity for excise
taxes you have configured on your item
card, and multiply with a excise duty
rate. Once when you get this final
value, system will have everything
calculated and when you register, it
will finish in excise transaction logs.
So, now let's switch to demo to see how
it works in a practice.
First, I want to show you
items.
How we configure our items. And I
already have
some configuration here.
So, I have the last fast tab. Now, new
fast tab, excise taxes. Keep in mind
that excise taxes is independent app.
So, if you don't calculate, you can
easily remove this app outside of of the
system. So, you don't need to choose
excise tax type. I will show how we
making this excise tax types,
as I already shown on the slides. And
then, if I choose plastic, I will say
what is quantity for excise taxes
on this item. What does it mean? This
item
can be weight, for example, 30 kilos.
But it has 4 kilograms because kilogram
is excise tax
unit of measure, 4 kg of plastics
inside.
So, system will not calculate whole
weight from this item, but only what is
plastic because we are paying plastic
tax based on a plastic amount in your
items.
So, this is configuration what you have.
I have this configured for few other
items. So, you can see here.
But I just do not wanted
don't I didn't want to forget EPR and
CBAM. So, still on sustainability fast
tab, you can use in combination. You can
configure if um
source for emissions is coming from
vendor. So, this is for
CBAM and you can run CBAM compliance.
Or if you have some item, for example,
another one, I already configure
EPR category. So, in EPR category, you
can choose one of them and you need to
configure material
composition. Why I want to show you?
There are some misunderstandings
when you have more different things for
taxation related to the plastic tax.
Plastic tax is only plastic tax. But if
you have situation that you need to
register EPR, this is not a regular
excise duty for plastic taxes. This is
completely different. So, if you have
all these subjects, for example,
plastic, leather, textile, depends what
is required to be taxed, you will use
EPR and item material composition. Here,
you can configure weight for all of
them, what is EPR fee rate, and so on,
so on. So, once when you have
configured, system will automatically
say what is EPR weight and what is EPR
fees per unit. So, this part is not
directly connected with excise taxes.
Even we are using the same excise tax
journal, they can work in a parallel.
But, what you cannot you cannot combine
uh plastic excise tax with some other
excise taxes here from different types.
This is not possible.
And now, let's look in excise
taxes types.
So, what is necessary for you to make
setup? I already configure some alcohol,
cannabis, cigarettes, petrol, plastic,
sugar. They're just ideas uh for where
um
in the most of countries is required
some type of tax calculate excise tax or
excise duty calculations. So, I will
make a look in the plastic tax, for
example. And I already configure that
this is based on weight. This is how it
should be calculated, but as I
mentioned, you have different. If this
is sugar tax, you can use sugar content
or active content, volume, pure alcohol
quantity, and so on. So, okay, here I'm
using weight. What else I need to do? I
need to configure entry permissions. And
you can enter one by one, or you can use
action set of default permissions, so
system will offer all types behavior
system, and only what you need to do is
to mark what is allowed. I have here
plastic tax is used on a purchase, so I
have purchase positive
output assembly output. If you don't
want to use positive adjustment, just
disable it. So, this is on you how you
will make a setup. And I mentioned the
last setup is item and fixed asset
rates.
That means you need to configure that
source type used for calculation will be
item or item and fixed assets, and what
is excise duty rate.
Of course, effective from date for
calculation. So, that's it. Uh there is
nothing specific more to have here. I
already have posted purchase invoices,
so there is nothing uh specific in
purchase invoices. You just need to uh
post them. And uh I will open
excise journal.
So, now we have plastic.
What I said, if you are using excise as
a type in a batch, you need to decide
excise tax type filter. So, this is
connected only with the model of excise.
But, if you are using type CBM EPR, you
will leave this empty. This is something
what we already had from the previous
wave. So, okay, let's use plastic
because I already have uh posted um
and uh entries uh invoices. So, once
when I generate tax entries, I need to
say, "Okay, what is posting date?" And
starting and ending date, I already
configure. I think that I have all
entries in June 27.
Okay. I got 18 lines. So, what you will
have here, excise entry type, if this is
purchase,
if original document is invoice,
document number for
that means journal document number. So,
you have descriptions, if this is vendor
or customer, if we this come from sales
process.
Partner number, then we have all these
calculations, all items uh number,
description. Now, about unit of measure.
Do not forget what I mentioned. This is
regular source unit of measure. This is
unit of measure from your item, but this
is excise tax unit of measure you
configure on uh for this item. So,
source quantity in item ledger entry is
15.
But, multiplier from item card is four.
So, that means that 4 kg in one piece of
item desk is plastic. And then, we have
15 * 4 * 25 as this is excise duty, we
will get final amount for payment
$1,500.
So, uh if you remember, I mentioned this
caption for plastic tax. You can see
here in a bracket plastic tax, excise
duty plastic tax, and so on. So, if you
choose, for example, alcohol,
you can see alcohol excise duty alcohol
excise duty, so it depends how we
calculated. And what I wanted to show
you that
this uh EPR, for example, EPR is based
on sales. So, if I run calculate,
I should get some lines. I already have
configured on sales invoices, so it
works. So, that means if you are using
plastic tax calculation, it will not
exclude completely EPR calculation. They
are completely different, so you can use
both of them or CBM as well.
So, this time we have different
calculation.
Uh we have from uh item, from customer.
Previous type we had vendor, now we have
customer. So, what we need to do? We
need to register.
It will be
Um okay, I didn't specify emission,
sorry. But, let's go back to plastic. We
can register it. And once when we
register, everything will be there. So,
eventually I can check
excise taxes transaction logs.
And you can see all these transactions I
have. It can be related to different
types. You have here excise uh log type
excise or CBM EPR, so you can combine
all them all of them will be in the same
place. Currently, we do not have any
specific report for
um showing, so you can export in Excel,
but plan is to continue invest invest
into this direction and this
functionality, so we will see what will
be next delivered.
So, this is shortly about demo
and about how excise taxes and duties
works.
So, we are on the end of this session,
so I will just remind you use some of
these links. You can find the
interesting content, or go to LinkedIn,
or watch our YouTube sessions.
So, that's it from me about excise taxes
or excise duties.
Thank you for watching this video.